<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Good Technology Project</title>
    <description>Research on how to do good with software
</description>
    <link>http://goodtechnologyproject.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://goodtechnologyproject.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 17:41:10 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 17:41:10 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tech consultancy for non-profits: an interview with EyeSeeTea</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/EyeSeeTea-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;EyeSeeTea&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adrian Quintana Pérez, José García Muñoz, and Ignacio Foche Pérez form
&lt;a href=&quot;www.eyeseetea.com&quot;&gt;EyeSeeTea&lt;/a&gt;, a software consultancy focussed on serving the non-profit sector. We
talked to them about how non-profits use software, and whether their approach to
developing it is changing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What made you start EyeSeeTea?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three of us were studying together on a Masters course in telecommunication
for developing countries. Afterwards, we talked to see if we could do some work
together, maybe publish something. Then a year ago we decided to start the
company. That happened in quite an easy way - we found a client who needed us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of people trying to do telecommunications work in
developing countries, but they are following a research approach. There aren’t
many people working as professional software developers in this area. So we’re
doing quite well - for a startup!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there a lot of demand for what you have to offer?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of people who could do what we do, but they need to get paid!
There are plenty of skilled people, and people who know what’s needed in the
field, and people who have access to money. But there aren’t often
people who have all three, and that’s where we fit, in the junction of those
worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small nonprofits don’t usually hire people like us. They are more likely to have one computer
specialist who does everything. Bigger nonprofits are more likely to have the money to
hire a company. Often we take public contracts to do work for a government,
university, or large nonprofit. There is quite a bit of work in the research
sector for implementation work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big nonprofits, on the other hand, are more and more hiring internal people to
do this kind of job. It’s a new thing for them, they are not yet used to hiring
software developers. They often think it should be a volunteer role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So why do they hire you instead of their own developers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, our clients know us and we have a close relationship with them.
We tend to know clients in advance. It will be a key challenge to go beyond
people we know. Having a few contracts with well known nonprofits will help
build our reputation and make it easier to get more clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there room for more organizations like yours?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The space is increasing in size, it’s growing every year. Technology is becoming
more important and people are starting to understand that sometimes you need to
hire a professional. There is definitely a gap, but it’s not huge. There are
only three of us, and we’re not even working full time yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until this year, the usual way we’ve found to start a development project wasn’t
to focus on technology first. NGOs in the past were not used to hiring a tech
company. They might just hire one person or not think it’s important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For software, nonprofits used to think that they could get a couple of
volunteers for free. But now they are beginning to understand that if you want
to meet a deadline and get a quality product then you need to pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All our work is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/EyeSeeTea&quot;&gt;open source&lt;/a&gt;, but there is a difference between open
source and free of charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there other organizations doing this, like you are? What would happen if you didn’t do it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we create the need at the nonprofit, by showing them what they could
do with our help. In other cases there is competition for a contract. We tender
a bid, and they do the price comparison. For a university that has money for a
project, there will usually be competition between projects as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you know the company - maybe you’ve done a small project for them already - 
you have a better chance. But you have to get a foot in the door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means it’s very important to have contacts in the field. All of us have
worked in this field as volunteers before. I think to access this kind of market
you really have to start as a volunteer, so that you know the people and the needs. If you
can find the need, and the people, and the budget, then maybe you can start
something, but that’s not easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What skillset do you wish you had? What skills are needed by your customers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment we say we can do anything, because we are just starting!
Everything is changing, new technologies all the time, so you have to be
flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data mining is everywhere, analysing metadata etc. Big data is important, lots
of organizations simply have a huge amount of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the ACM Dev conference there were a lot of presentations about data analysis.
That is a big trend in this world. Organizations and donors want to know what is
happening with funds, how to improve efficiency, etc. There is a gap in
data science for this field. Not many universities work in this kind of analysis
in the developing world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you consider working directly for a nonprofit?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignacio used to work for one, a small NGO, working in Peru and Colombia. And he
was a volunteer in a bigger one. But this field depends heavily on the economy.
In Spain, for example, all the budget for development was cut suddenly. It can
be very unstable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adrian came from the research world. His involvement in development was through
volunteering in his free time. When he got hired by UCL he sent his CV to a
couple of places. But it’s difficult to get hired by a nonprofit. There are a
lot of good people applying to few positions. Nonprofits could hire more people
if they would pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What kind of work have you ended up doing so far?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve done a variety of things: network infrastructure, mobile apps, web,
technological audits. All of our code is open-source, so you can see it on our
website. It is nice that we’ve been able to see many different aspects of
telecommunications. We’d like to keep doing that!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/05/30/interview-with-eyeseetea</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/05/30/interview-with-eyeseetea</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ICT in social enterprise: an interview with Lucie Klarsfeld from Hystra</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/lucie_klarsfeld.png&quot; alt=&quot;Lucie Klarsfeld&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lucie Klarsfeld is a Senior Product Manager at Hystra, a strategy consultancy
focussed on social enterprises targeting the Base of the Pyramid. We talked to her
to learn more about the social enterprise sector as a whole, and pariticularly the
role of technology.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Could you give us a brief overview of what Hystra does?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re a strategy consultancy company that specialises in social business and
so-called Base of the Pyramid (BoP) markets. By a “social business” we include
anyone that uses market mechanisms to address social issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, this focus comes from our founder, Olivier Kayser, who previously
worked for both McKinsey and Ashoka. At the end of his time there, he could see
a lot of synergies between the social entrepreneurs that Ashoka was helping -
who were good at finding local solutions, but not necessarily so good at (or
interested in) scaling up - and multinational corporations - who are less good
at (or interested in) social innovation, but whose entire “raison d’être” are
to adapt and replicate solutions that work across countries. So the aim was to
try and combine these two worlds, and in particular to figure out how large
corporations could help social enterprises to scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first report that we did was on 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://hystra.com/energy&quot;&gt;access to energy for the poorest&lt;/a&gt;. We’ve
kept a pretty similar methodology since then, which is to look at what worked.
We try to go in with no preconceptions, and look at what business models there
are in a sector. Then we select a representative sample of businesses in the
sector, and we visit them to understand better how they work and why they
haven’t scaled further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then use this research to help specific actors to be more efficient, or to
scale better. That is either with large corporations to define how they can
profitably work with the base of the pyramid, or with social businesses to help
them scale their strategy, e.g. we help them write business plans or raise
funds. We also work with other organizations like aid agencies or foundations
to help them define their strategy to support social businesses or work with
the private sector, in order to achieve their development objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give you an example of what this can look like concretely: at the end of the
energy project, we gave some recommendations to the sponsors. To Total we
recommended that they start using their brand and network in Africa to start
selling solar lanterns. Back in 2010 the market was very nascent, with a few
products out there, mostly of poor quality. When Total brought in their brand
and distribution skills, they were able to build much more consumer trust in
the product, and help the few quality manufacturers get consistent orders and
scale up production. They’ve sold 1.4 million to date, which makes them the
largest commercial distributor of this product in the developing world. These
are the kind of synergies that we’re looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So the focus is not on starting businesses, but rather scaling them?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, although you could argue that in the case I just mentioned, Total didn’t
have any presence in that solar light business beforehand. We’re strategy
consultants, so we can start from scratch to build a strategy for a new entrant
in the sector!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You publish all your research publically, on your website?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, that’s a condition for the 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://hystra.com/open-source-reports/&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; we do. It’s also why the entrepreneurs
that we study agree to participate, and to open their books to us. Publishing
it to the world gives them publicity, and they have full control over the
material that we actually publish. We often sign an NDA with them, so they
usually give us much more information than we put in the case studies, which we
use to create derived statistics or benchmarks that get published in aggregate,
not revealing their individual confidential data while helping the sector
progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you prioritise which business models you pick for the report?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a set of criteria. We want a project that really solves the issue,
which isn’t to be taken for granted! The project also has to have a certain
scale. For example, when producing the agriculture report on &lt;a href=&quot;http://hystra.com/smallholder&quot;&gt;Smallholder
Farmers and Businesses&lt;/a&gt;, 
almost all the projects we picked had over 10,000
customers. If it’s below that, we consider that it’s too new a project for us
to be able to draw many conclusions on what works. The project also has to be
financially sustainable: we don’t want models that are purely philanthropy;
though we don’t necessarily want models that have already broken even,
otherwise we would not find much… But we do look for models that have the
ability to break even at some point, even if they have not already done so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first phase of our research we read reports and interview the authors,
and ask them which projects they think are the most successful given our
criteria; as well as to refer us to other experts. There comes a point when we
keep hearing the same things from experts who start referring the same projects
and people to interview, and then we know we’ve covered most of the ground. We
also do our own research, and in total we usually find between 150 and 300
projects per sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also looking for patterns of similar projects that emerge, so we can pick
representative examples as case studies. In the case of 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://hystra.com/leveraging-ict&quot;&gt;ICT&lt;/a&gt; it looked like the
business models were either one-way information passing, two-way information
passing, or crowd-sourcing/crowd-funding solutions. In each of these clusters
we select the best projects according to our criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What sources do you use for the research process?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We try to get input from a variety of sources. We try to talk to the large
industry players; large institutions like the World Bank; other successful
social enterprises; and some academics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report mentions that there wasn’t much work on impact, and people weren’t
doing cost-effectiveness research. Do you do any of that work, or do you see
others doing it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ICT report is a few years old, but even returning to it recently there
still isn’t much work on cost-effectiveness. ICT in development is still quite
new, and evolving very fast. And it’s really only in the last few years that
social enterprises have started to get their ICT systems in order, using CRM or
sales force management systems, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also quite difficult to assess the impact of ICT. In particular, I think
it would be difficult to single out the effect of ICT on their overall impact
of a project. If it’s not primarily an ICT project, if ICT is a tool, which it
usually is, then it’s very difficult to say whether it was the ICT that
mattered or the other parts of the business model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even systems that are very heavy on ICT have other important aspects. For
example, one of the reasons that mobile money hasn’t taken off as well in
places beyond Kenya is because of the critical importance of setting up an
adequately sized agent network for cashing in and out. That’s the part that’s
proven hard to replicate!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s particularly hard to bring in new, unfamiliar ICT systems, as the benefit
has to be quite high in order to get people to buy into what may appear as a
new, risky, system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a role for ICT companies to provide tech services that
assist other organization doing more direct development or social business
work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think about the Good Technology Project?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s needed. Many social businesses would benefit from e.g. ICT
volunteers to go and help set up their IT systems. One thing that would be very
helpful would be to have some kind of comparison of the available tools. Even
now that social enterprises are starting to improve their ICT systems, it’s not
easy for them to do it well, design an adequate tool and choose the right
partner for it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think the prospects are for developed world entrepreneurs trying to
start social enterprises in the developing world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s important to spend a good period of time exploring and learning
about what’s already being done on the ground, rather than start from a blank
sheet of paper with possibly pre-conceived ideas. Go and work for an existing
organization, start to see what the existing models are in developing
countries. If they’re entrepreneurial, they’ll spot opportunities to make
things better once they have been part of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t start from nothing - there’s no way to avoid understanding the
problem and doing your market research! Especially since developing countries
are a new environment for developed world entrepreneurs, it’s important to
actually be there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What areas are currently neglected in the ICT space?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ICT is primarily used as a component of a larger system or business model, but
in and of itself, it’s proven particularly useful for transferring money in
places where that is difficult, and also in bringing information where it is
missing and can make a life changing difference (e.g., getting market prices
for farmers, or receiving quality medical information in remote communities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So looking at it from a general perspective, you can look for places where
there are information asymmetries, or where there isn’t communication and there
should be. Perhaps you can find some opportunities there.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2016 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/05/21/interview-with-hystra</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/05/21/interview-with-hystra</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data science competitions for good: an interview with Isaac Slaviitt from DrivenData</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/drivendata.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The DrivenData team&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Isaac Slavitt (right) is a co-founder and data scientist at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drivendata.org/&quot;&gt;DrivenData&lt;/a&gt;. Also pictured are co-founders Greg Lipstein (left) and Peter Bull (center). DrivenData hosts data science competitions that focus on social impact. The team also &lt;a href=&quot;http://drivendata.co/&quot;&gt;works directly with organizations&lt;/a&gt;, helping them harness their data in order to work smarter and carry out their missions more effectively. We talked to Isaac to know more about how they are applying data science for doing good.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did DrivenData get started? What are you trying to do and what are your future plans?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DrivenData actually started off as a grad school project. My co-founders and I wanted to work on a research project in machine learning that was technically interesting but that also had some kind of social impact aspect, and we actually found it really hard to find relevant problems with available data. We knew there were many others in the field who were excited about that type of work, so we had the idea to build a platform specifically targeted at running data science competitions for social good. We started talking to nonprofits early on and the initial response was very positive, so we ended up launching our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drivendata.org/competitions/4/&quot;&gt;first for-prize competition&lt;/a&gt; soon after the platform was up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With DrivenData, we have two main goals. The first is to get more people interested in applying their data skills to relevant problems, and providing an easy and fun way to start getting involved. The other goal is direct impact: working with mission-driven organizations to help them frame their data challenges, making those available to the data science community on our platform whenever possible, and helping them integrate the results back into their workflow. Of course, not all problems that nonprofits face fit neatly into a predictive modeling context, so our team also does consulting work for mission-driven organizations directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as future plans go, on the competition front there is a lot of overhead work in getting a competition ready, particularly if the organization we are working with doesn’t have data scientists on staff. We have been thinking about how to scale the competition preparation part of the platform, and in the medium term we want to figure out how to make this a more repeatable, streamlined process. In terms of the direct consulting work that we do, it has been really rewarding to work with organizations on their data and technology challenges and we plan to continue doing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you factor-in impact in the work you do? Can you give us an example of a high-impact project you have undertaken?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on projects with real impact is very important to us. We tend to think about the impact of the competitions we run in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One is the direct impact of the solution for the organization that we’re partnering with. We take that into account both while refining the problem as well as in finding partners to work with that we think will be able to benefit the most from winning solutions. Sometimes that means that they’re really interested in what insights they can learn from the models in carrying out their mission, and sometimes it means finding organizations who are in a good position to actually implement the winning solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second way we look at the platform’s impact is in raising awareness about the opportunities that exist in applying data science for good, and by providing people a platform to get involved. One metric for this is the participation level in our competitions. We get participants from all over the world, and the number of competitors and submissions has been increasing with each competition. Wherever possible, we try to look for ways to keep the data and problem open for people to keeping working on and learning from even after the main competition has ended. That’s one of the reasons we generally require winners to release their solutions under an open source license.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of a high impact project is our &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.drivendata.org/2015/11/06/keeping-it-fresh-results/&quot;&gt;“Keeping It Fresh” competition&lt;/a&gt;. The basic setup there is that the City of Boston has a large number of restaurants but only a limited number of food inspectors. The idea of this competition was that there must be a better method for choosing restaurants to inspect than sending the inspectors out at random, so the task was to find predictive signal using a large dataset of Yelp reviews in order to flag restaurants that could be potential food safety violators. One of the fun things about this competition was that, for their final submissions, competitors were actually making food violations predictions about the next few months — so it wasn’t just hold-out data, they were actually testing their models by trying to predict future events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the competition, there was a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hbs.edu/faculty/Pages/item.aspx?num=50429&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; published about it by economists at Harvard who concluded that these methods could make cities 30-50% more efficient in their use of food inspectors’ time. That’s a nice win for public health and public sector effectiveness. Even better, the same methodology could be applied to other cities as well, which could act as a multiplier for the impact of this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What led you to choose the competition format as opposed to hackathons and/or volunteering?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What interested us about the competition format is that it scales globally because of the way it is structured. This format is particularly well suited for complex problems that could benefit from a large number of people trying out a large number of different approaches. For some really hard problems, particularly involving &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_language_processing&quot;&gt;NLP&lt;/a&gt; or computer vision, it’s great to have hundreds of people trying thousands of different approaches to feature selection, model tuning, and so forth—far more than any one team could try in a reasonable amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The limitation of the format is that not all problems can be framed as competitions. For example, there are tons of really important problems that organizations face where the data doesn’t fit neatly into a statistical modeling question, or where the dataset is not large enough, or where they are looking for more open ended research or systems development. These problems are often better tackled through volunteering, and there are some fantastic organizations out there like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datakind.org&quot;&gt;DataKind&lt;/a&gt; who facilitate working directly with organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What factors do you consider while selecting partners to work with?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three main considerations for selecting partners to work with: The first and most important is that the proposed problem should be interesting to participants and have a high potential for impact. The second is the technical and data maturity level of the organization. Third and equally important is having data-savvy people in the organization that could take the winning entry and integrate it into their workflow, or at least develop a plan for extracting value from the end products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are open to working with partners throughout the world — in fact our most recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drivendata.org/competitions/9/&quot;&gt;competition&lt;/a&gt; centered on an organization based in Morocco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Based on your knowledge of applying data science for social good, do you see any problem or area that is neglected?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think just being able to capture and store the right data in general, and then data quality in particular, is a hard problem for many nonprofits. That challenge definitely isn’t specific to the social sector, but in our experience many organizations are struggling to keep up with the private sector in that respect. Even large organizations with permanent IT staff typically lack dedicated software engineers or data scientists, and the existing staff may not have the bandwidth to spend a lot of time thinking about how they generate and warehouse information. Taken together, that means that building systems and processes for data collection and preservation is often not an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those data issues may not seem pressing on any given day because the nonprofit staff are busy working on the primary mission, but at some point they are probably going to want to learn from their data, and the missed opportunities happening right now are going to make that difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field will continue to get more mature and I think there are going to be more and more data scientists wanting to work with nonprofits which is great news, but five years down the line if organizations don’t have the right data or if the data has serious quality and consistency issues then they may find themselves starting from scratch. Since many nonprofits could use some help on this front, here’s a big opportunity for data practitioners to get involved right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What advice do you have for someone wanting to use data science and software skills for good?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the growing popularity of data science in recent years and the resulting surge in demand, nonprofits are finding it difficult to compete in hiring full time staff from that talent pool. That also means there are lots of great opportunities for people with the desire to help, and it isn’t necessary to know the latest machine learning algorithms to contribute — many organizations have a lot to gain even through relatively simple automation of their day to day processes, so there is huge opportunity for data scientists and software engineers of all skill levels. For example: at many nonprofits, basic projects like setting up a data collection pipeline would be a big win since that would enable them to apply more advanced techniques in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to get involved is by volunteering directly with nonprofits, volunteering through organizations such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datakind.org&quot;&gt;DataKind&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeforamerica.org/&quot;&gt;Code For America&lt;/a&gt;, or by participating in competitions like the ones on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drivendata.org/&quot;&gt;our platform&lt;/a&gt;. There is also still plenty of room in this space for new organizations that adopt one or a mix of the prevailing models, whether that is volunteer driven consulting, fee-based consulting, or online crowdsourcing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would encourage people to look locally. There is a lot of activity happening around data science for good in most cities, in the form of Meetups, DataKind chapters, conferences, and so on. But even if there aren’t many events in your area, there is almost certainly a nonprofit nearby that would love some help with their technical or data challenges. Even if you are just getting started in the field, you may be able to make a surprisingly meaningful contribution with your skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can sign up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drivendata.org/accounts/signup/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to be notified about and participate in DrivenData competitions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 21:20:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/05/15/interview-with-drivendata</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/05/15/interview-with-drivendata</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data science for good: an interview with Lauren Haynes of the Center for Data Science and Public Policy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/lauren_haynes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lauren Haynes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lauren Haynes is a senior project manager at the Center for Data Science and Public Policy (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dsapp.org/&quot;&gt;DSAPP&lt;/a&gt;) at the University of Chicago. We talked to her to know more about the potential of data science for doing good.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you tell us about your journey so far in applying technology for good?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a degree in general engineering from UIUC with a minor in computer science and human-computer interaction. While in college, I was quite involved with &lt;a href=&quot;http://dsapp.org/&quot;&gt;Alternative Spring Break&lt;/a&gt; and went on seven service trips. I then went on to work with Accenture Technology Labs where I was involved with cutting edge research projects. I always had an inclination towards social good - so when one of my colleagues invited me to join &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theounce.org/&quot;&gt;Ounce of Prevention Fund&lt;/a&gt;, which does a lot of work in the area of early childhood education, I gladly accepted. As the IT Manager there, I revamped the IT infrastructure of the organization and also catered to its technology needs. At the Ounce, I also got a chance to gain an understanding of the internal dynamics of the working of an NGO. I then went to work as the product manager at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.giveforward.com/&quot;&gt;GiveForward&lt;/a&gt; - a crowdfunding platform for compassionate giving. This role was unique and enjoyable since it had both a high technology component as well as a high social good component. Since last May, I have been working with the Data Science for Social Good Fellowship (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dssg.uchicago.edu/&quot;&gt;DSSG&lt;/a&gt;) wherein we get 42 undergrad and graduate students each year to do data science projects for nonprofits and government agencies. The projects topics run the gamut from education, healthcare, environment, public safety, criminal justice… you name it. Some examples of problems we tackle in our program are prediction questions e.g. which participants are likely to drop out of a program; another example would be resource allocation questions e.g. we can inspect only a 100 buildings out of a 1000 - which ones are most likely to be noncompliant. I am also serving as the board vice-chair for &lt;a href=&quot;http://alternativebreaks.org/&quot;&gt;Break Away&lt;/a&gt; wherein I provide guidance on using technology to efficiently manage their operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the awareness level among nonprofits regarding what technology and data science can do for them?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of nonprofits I have interacted with do not have a deep understanding of what technology and data science can do for them. Through our interaction with nonprofits, we have been educating them on this aspect and what it would require of them. We have also been working on a &lt;a href=&quot;http://dsapp.org/learning/datamaturity/&quot;&gt;data maturity framework&lt;/a&gt; that talks about the different stages an organization might be in, from an organization, technology, and data perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there any high impact cause areas that are particularly suited to apply data science?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Application of data science to social good problems is a relatively new concept and this is true for most cause areas. The sector is not incentivised to bring talented data scientists in, and even in cases where a nonprofit is interested and has the resources to hire a data scientist, it takes a special kind of person to take up that assignment, since this person might be the only data science hire and would have to run the show alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of types of problems, I think early identification and early prediction problems, and resource allocation problems are particularly suited to applying data science. While on the topic of impact, it is vital that data scientists work closely with the community partners, spend time getting to know the organization and their pain points, and build solutions that are actionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there any specific product or service gaps that a tech/data science startup could serve?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you individually talk to nonprofits, a lot of opportunities come up. One finds that many of the tools and processes used by nonprofits are primitive and not very user-friendly. The solutions needed are actually quite simple, provided you have the industry context. One example would be using marketing analytics for fundraising and advocacy, another would be automating day-to-day processes, and there are many other simple tools that could really help nonprofits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of data science, I think a consultation based model is more likely to work: The Center for Data Science and Public Policy (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dsapp.org/&quot;&gt;DSAPP&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://theimpactlab.co/&quot;&gt;The Impact Lab&lt;/a&gt; are two examples of such organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there any skills that are particularly important for someone wanting to work in the tech for good space?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of communication and listening cannot be overstated. It is really important to first listen to and understand the problems that the organization you are working with faces, and then clearly communicate what you propose to do and why. You need to meet people where they are at and have this conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you your outlook for the future of this field?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Application of data science for social good is a relatively new field, and looking into the future one can expect lots of opportunities. A challenge for nonprofits and the government would be knowing what’s possible with technology and data science, arranging the resources to hire talented individuals, and efficiently managing these individuals and projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: The Center for Data Science and Public Policy is looking to hire a software / data engineer. Details of the opening can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://dsapp.org/jobs-software-engineer/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2016 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/04/30/data-science-for-good-an-interview-with-lauren-haynes-of-the-center-for-data-science-and-public-policy</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/04/30/data-science-for-good-an-interview-with-lauren-haynes-of-the-center-for-data-science-and-public-policy</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ICT for international development: an interview with Sam Sudar</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell us a bit about your how you got into ICT for Development (ICTD).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://samsudar.com/&quot;&gt;I’m a PhD student&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Washington in Seattle. I’m doing my thesis on leveraging web tech on poorly connected regions and this is the theme throughout everything I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started in the tech for development group working on &lt;a href=&quot;https://opendatakit.org/&quot;&gt;Open Data Kit&lt;/a&gt; - a platform to help researchers and NGOs collect and manage data. The first version, which is widely used, is a way to use Excel to specify a form in native Android that looks a bit like a web form. This makes it easy to create a form and collect data from it. It’s used in over 100 countries and the Red Cross used it extensively after the Haiti earthquake. I was involved in &lt;a href=&quot;https://opendatakit.org/use/2_0_tools/&quot;&gt;Open Data Kit 2.0&lt;/a&gt; which has the same functionality but in JavaScript and HTML to make more it more customizable. I’m not as involved in that now, but the paper on &lt;a href=&quot;https://samsudar.com/static/sudar_2015_duces.pdf&quot;&gt;simplifying mobile deployments in low resource settings&lt;/a&gt; that I presented at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://acmdev.org/&quot;&gt;London ICTD conference&lt;/a&gt; was motivated by that work. It came out of dealing with researchers who I often felt tried to overcomplicate things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last summer I interned at Google working in the Chrome for emerging regions group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago I was in Peru working with researchers who have a medical boat which goes up some of the Amazonian rivers to provide medical care for remote communities. I built an app that allows community agents in these remote communities to submit Open Data Kit forms via SMS. It turned out that they preferred WhatsApp to SMS and were talking directly to the doctors using it. That was working much better and the users were buying into it a lot more. So I was down there assessing cell signal and then this week I built a new version of the app that uses WhatsApp rather than SMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think of the argument that it might be higher impact to use older technologies because remaining opportunities involving old technology may not get as much attention because they’re unfashionable?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree and the work I’ve done thus far is not the bleeding edge - more like novel ways to use existing technologies. However, there are people who do more complicated things. For example &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.berkeley.edu/~shaddi/&quot;&gt;Shaddi Hasan&lt;/a&gt; started &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.endaga.com/&quot;&gt;Endaga&lt;/a&gt; which sets up cell phone towers in remote places like Papua, Indonesia and they recently got bought by Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think is neglected in ICTD? Where would you direct resources?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not sure I have an answer, but a broad thing I’ve noticed is that the bigger problems are understanding how to use existing technology. Many of the existing problems that global health researchers have are not things that need new applications to solve. It’s more that they don’t have a good sense of what’s possible and what’s an easy way to do things, and even if they had an idea of that they wouldn’t know how to go about doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be good if you could set up a website that provides step-by-step instructions on how to solve common problems in international development with technology. For example, ‘If you need to do data collection, here are the components and here’s how you set them up.’ Data collection is particularly amenable to this because you don’t need a programmer. As long as you know the tools to use and are computer literate and you could piece it together. Perhaps you could have instructions for a bunch of other common problems like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why don’t people in development know what’s possible in tech and why don’t they hire tech people?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People in international development often value involvement of tech beyond the added value that tech brings. If they have a project and they think they could involve tech, that makes it sexier. The decision to involve technology is more of a knee-jerk reaction than something that comes after thinking ‘What do we really need technology for?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there is a shortage of people who have a good breadth of technical skills to be able to put all the parts of a solution together and to be able to advise on what is difficult and what is easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why aren’t those people in development organisations?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know whether or not those kinds of people are being hired. But I know it’s expensive to do anything involving code and so often only the biggest organisations can afford it and these big organisations are less inclined to open-source their work and document what they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think people often don’t know how to apply technology - it’s can be a bit of a hammer looking for a nail. There are cases like data collection where it works well, but other cases where it doesn’t work so well - such as when people build one-off applications. People don’t think ‘If only we had an app to do this’ because they don’t know what they need. Tech can be helpful but it’s not the missing link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Open Data Kit message board there is a mix of people. Some people have well thought-out questions. And then there’s other people who don’t know how to get started because they need basic IT support and it’s hard to do that remotely. It’s also often hard to get a sense of what people want from tech. There is often disagreement within the organisation about what is wanted. It’s then very difficult to come in and solve their problems with technology because they don’t know what they want. Rarely do people have a problem that is well-specified. It’s more like ‘There is something that is hard for us, how can we make this easier’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Good Technology Project had something where people could submit a request for help, that would be useful. It would need to filter out people who are not serious. But if you force people to put some effort then you could have tech people respond. That’s missing more than building code. For example, in Peru they had stopped using WhatsApp because every 3 months if you don’t upgrade WhatsApp it locks you out until you upgrade. Everyone using the app thought it was broken. I was baffled - I was expecting to be surprised, but I was surprised even more because it said clearly what the problem was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think of the approach of academia to ICTD as compared to other groups?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not thrilled with the academic approach. There are often a lot of throwaway prototypes and overreaching claims. It’s a weird space because people are doing work trying to solve real problems but they aren’t bound to deliver anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s rare to find a project that actually productizes a prototype that a paper was published about. Most people don’t have the resources or time to productize it and it’s really hard to do. It’s hard to release a project that is based on an academic project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative to that is a paper that may or may not work. I think if you don’t release the code you say you ran I’m suspicious. Especially in ICTD you have a problem where the paper says something works but you don’t actually know that. For example, people are really into SMS reminders at the moment. There are projects, but it takes more decision making and work than people realise. Just because a paper shows one can do something, doesn’t mean you can do it easily. Often people believe it can be done effortlessly and someone else can maintain it for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who does the best work in this field?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard great things about &lt;a href=&quot;http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/labs/india/&quot;&gt;Microsoft Research India&lt;/a&gt;. They have a good reputation and seem to do stuff that does work. My favorite project of theirs one to make sure TB patients actually took their pills. They printed codes in pill containers so you when you push out the pill you can see the code and text it in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like what the Chrome team at Google does (although I’m biased) with &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.googleblog.com/2015/11/a-new-way-to-save-data-with-chrome-on.html&quot;&gt;data saver&lt;/a&gt;. You can turn on an option in Chrome for Android that will send all of your traffic to a server they run then it compresses the data and prefetches things which speeds it up and lowers data use. They’ve got &lt;a href=&quot;http://research.google.com/pubs/pub43447.html&quot;&gt;a paper about it&lt;/a&gt;. If this was an academic project there would be lots of implementation problems, but Google has managed to solve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consultants can also do well because they have the resources to do projects that they know they can meet the requirements of. It’s very expensive though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the career paths in this field?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest thing is getting experience with groups that think they need some sort of technological assistance. It would be good if there was a way to put NGOs in touch with tech people, even just to answer questions on what kind of solution is needed for the NGO’s problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why doesn’t this communication between NGOs and tech people happen?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global health researchers usually don’t think to turn to the web and try to find someone to help. Often researchers don’t realise that they don’t need something complicated and just need someone to walk through things. The flip side of this is the Gates Foundation who will just hire a consultant and they can pay, and the consultants expect to get paid. But I think there would be tech people happy to do voluntary work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there would be more to be gained by tech people giving the lay of the land to NGOs rather than building an app. There’s more to go wrong in building an app and often the NGOs don’t know what they need.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2016 19:35:26 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/04/29/ict-for-international-development-an-interview-with-sam-sudar</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/04/29/ict-for-international-development-an-interview-with-sam-sudar</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Persistently neglected causes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A heuristic that we often use when assessing causes is that of &lt;em&gt;neglectedness&lt;/em&gt;.
If a cause is neglected, then that means that it is not receiving an amount of
attention commensurate to it’s seriousness. Given that most causes suffer from
diminishing marginal returns on investment, if less has been invested then we
should expect there to be especially cost-effective projects still available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not all neglectedness is made equal. Some causes are only neglected
&lt;em&gt;transiently&lt;/em&gt;. That is, they aren’t receiving
much attention now, but it’s clear that that will change in the relatively near
future. An example is mobile services for the poor. This area has been
neglected for a long time because the infrastructure and the handset penetration
were not there, but that that is &lt;a href=&quot;http://guardian.ng/technology/africas-mobile-phone-penetration-now-67/&quot;&gt;changing&lt;/a&gt;.
Hence, interest is picking up, and
we should expect to see an increasing amount of resources directed there over
the coming years. So it’s likely that many potential projects in this
area will happen anyway in the next couple of decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a cause is only transiently neglected then the impact of paying attention to
it is lesser. If someone else is going to do the work eventually,
then by doing it now you have simply brought that time forward.
That can be a great thing - getting a malaria vaccine even a year earlier would
be fantastic! But it’s even better if we can address a cause that is
&lt;em&gt;persistently&lt;/em&gt; neglected. In that case you are bringing forward an event which
might otherwise require an unusual combination of factors to occur, and
therefore probably wouldn’t happen for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why might a cause be persistently neglected? One reason can be that there are persistent
obstacles to addressing it. For example, many good things can be done by for-profit companies,
but there are a number of problems that can persistently obstruct for-profit
solutions, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The beneficiaries of the project can’t pay for it. For example, attempts to
sell high-end electronics to the poor are likely to fail, not because
the customers wouldn’t benefit from them, but because they simply can’t afford them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s difficult to capture the value created by the project. This can happen
because the beneficiaries are not the customers. Anything with large positive externalities has this
problem, such as infrastructural projects or provision of public goods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a more profitable way to deliver the product to the customers that
doesn’t have as much social benefit. For example, one could sell a farmer the
ability to get to market by selling them a vehicle, or by building
a road. Selling just a vehicle may be more profitable, but the road may
benefit many other people as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And almost any project can suffer from more general, but still persistent
problems, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The project requires unusual skills. You might need intimate knowledge of both
sub-Saharan Africa &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; modern financial markets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The project requires unusual knowledge. It is not at all obvious that
&lt;a href=&quot;www.spacex.com/about/capabilities&quot;&gt;you can build a cheaper rocket&lt;/a&gt;, but Elon
Musk had reason to believe that you could.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:secrets&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:secrets&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The benefits of the project are systematically undervalued (e.g. because they
accrue in the far future).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these obstacles can be addressed without actually attempting the
project! If the reason that nobody is building a cheaper rocket is because they
don’t believe that it’s possible, then it may be sufficient to challenge that
belief (by argument or example). At that point, if you’ve made a convincing
enough case, the problem may become only transiently neglected: now that people
realise that it’s possible, somebody else will probably do it soon.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:investment&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:investment&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
A lot of academic research falls into this camp - once someone has published a
proof of concept, it is only a matter of time before it is implemented.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hyperloop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hyperloop&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the best kind of project to actually work on, all other things being equal, is one which is both
persistently neglected and which cannot be easily made only transiently
neglected. This might be because the features that make it possible for you to
address it are personal or non-transferrable - unusual skills are a
good example of this. So if you can see a project idea which you think
relatively few people would even be able to attempt successfully, then it might
be a persistently neglected area, and so worthy of extra attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:secrets&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Peter Thiel in ‘Zero to One’ refers to these as “secrets”: things
that are hard to know, and not widely believed, but are nonetheless true.
If you have a secret, it’s likely that you have access to some unusual
evidence or theory that can make you particularly suited to address
particular problems. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:secrets&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:investment&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Of course, by the time you’ve demonstrated your principle, you
might have enough of a head start that it’s worth pushing on anyway! And it
may be a long road to convincing others of unusual beliefs. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:investment&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hyperloop&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Or, for a more industrial example, Elon Musk only produced a
white paper about his “Hyperloop” idea, and now there are several teams
working on an implementation. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hyperloop&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 12:58:26 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/04/03/persistent-neglectedness</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/04/03/persistent-neglectedness</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>LBRY and decentralised apps - an interview with Jeremy Kauffman</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jeremy Kauffman is the CEO of &lt;a href=&quot;http://lbry.io/&quot;&gt;LBRY&lt;/a&gt;, a decentralised content-publishing system. We talked to him because we want to know more about the potential of decentralised apps for doing good.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-you-doing&quot;&gt;What are you doing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to provide a simple search tool for movies, books, games, or any piece of content that can be published by anyone in the world. The big difference is that this network is completely decentralised - it’s powered by the computers of everyone in the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-the-more-technical-explanation&quot;&gt;What’s the more technical explanation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real insight of bitcoin isn’t that we can maintain account balances in a decentralised way. The big value is that there’s no one authority that has to be trusted but that you can reach still reach a consensus on &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; state. LBRY lets us reach a consensus on what name should go to what piece of information. This is a bit like a registry of domain names except that it doesn’t of relying on a centralised name registry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In LBRY people can claim a name like ‘wonderfullife’ and point it towards a piece of content and then when someone searches LBRY for it they will be able to access the content. When you register a name the name and the content it points to are broadcast out through the network and recorded on the LBRY blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our system is both a unit of account and a system of storing names and metadata. When someone claims a name, they don’t own that name or have permanent control. They reserve the name using some credits. Whoever has committed the most number of credits controls the resolution of the name. So they control what title and content a name like ‘wonderfullife’ returns. They can also set a price for viewing that content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our inspirations is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coase_theorem&quot;&gt;Coase theorem&lt;/a&gt;. This says that assuming that the rules are clear for how property is controlled, and transaction costs are low, property will be held by the person who gets the most value out of it. We think a name holds the most value when it returns what people are looking for under that name. We also think people would far prefer to purchase content from the actual rights holder than from a pirate. Rights holders will have strong incentives to participate in the system and won’t be stuck in a bittorrent-like system where there’s nothing they can do to remove pirated content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LBRY is not a good system to publish something on if it is illegal. In addition to the traditional legal remedies, people who don’t want the content on the LBRY network can take over the name to keep the content off the platform or to put the content on there themselves.  Say someone pays 5 credits to use the name ‘spiderman’ and has it return some Spider-Man movie that he doesn’t own and refuses to remove it. The owner, or the community, can pay 6 credits to take over the name ‘spiderman’ and either publish the movie there and set a price on it or just own the name to prevent anyone else from using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the pirate and the content owner get in a bidding war for the name, there will be a price at which the content owner thinks it’s worth paying more but the pirate doesn’t. This is because the consumers will be willing to pay more to the content owner than to the pirate. The owner can either let it the piracy happen, or they can join in and profit more than they would if they let it happen. The economic incentive is to participate rather than not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-this-important&quot;&gt;Why is this important?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a more computationally efficient way to distribute static data like movies and books which currently take up about 50% of internet traffic. By having a distributed system, popular content will be available to download from nearby locations thus saving computer power and electricity that is currently spent moving static data across long distances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal opinion is that there is another, bigger benefit. There are a lot of inefficiencies in how content and information is produced and shared today, and the incentives are set up to reward large media companies instead of creators. These media companies exist because they provide distribution but also because they leverage existing laws in a way that benefits neither the creators nor the consumers. In LBRY, the people who get squeezed are the middlemen, instead of the creators or consumers. The system at the moment inhibits us from making creative progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-values-are--you-trying-to-optimise-for&quot;&gt;What values are  you trying to optimise for?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking for myself, rather than the company, I’m motivated by the idea of human flourishing, pushing the boundaries of knowledge and of what we can accomplish as a species. I hope LBRY can make a contribution by reducing friction or making it cheaper to do that. I think working on LBRY is a chance to express and contribute towards these values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-you-have-an-ethicist-on-your-staff&quot;&gt;Why do you have an ethicist on your staff?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LBRY poses some difficult questions. At a certain point we’ll lose control of the system. What happens then if we release it and it doesn’t have the outcomes we expected? What are our obligations to prevent certain types of behaviour?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-there-a-risk-that-lbry-could-facilitate-people-publishing-information-that-could-be-used-for-bad-purposes&quot;&gt;Is there a risk that LBRY could facilitate people publishing information that could be used for bad purposes?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve tried to think through the design and make it in a way that will hope will steer it in a positive direction but I’m aware that it is hard to predict what will happen. Bitcoin has had problems with illegal activity but hopefully that’s something that it will progress out of as it becomes more mainstream. LBRY could be a platform to publish dangerous information, but that is true of the internet as a whole and I don’t think it’s possible to prevent people from sharing electronic information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-some-other-interesting-decentralised-app-projects&quot;&gt;What are some other interesting decentralised app projects?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.augur.net/&quot;&gt;Augur&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&quot;http://bitcoinhivemind.com/&quot;&gt;Hivemind&lt;/a&gt; - decentralised prediction markets. The nice thing about prediction markets is they incentivise people to be accurate and it would be good for humanity to have more accurate predictions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ethereum.org/&quot;&gt;Etherium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/02/07/lbry-and-decentralised-apps-an-interview-with-jeremy-kauffman</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/02/07/lbry-and-decentralised-apps-an-interview-with-jeremy-kauffman</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tech for effective charities - an interview with Ben Clifford from Good Code</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-good-code&quot;&gt;What is Good Code?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyletter.com/goodcode&quot;&gt;Good code&lt;/a&gt; is a meetup in London of software developers who work on projects for effective charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-good-code-get-started-what-are-you-trying-to-do&quot;&gt;How did good code get started? What are you trying to do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was interested in technology entrepreneurship and I wanted to do a lot of good. I thought a good potential customer for this would be poor people or charities that help them, especially as there is little incentive for other organisations to help them out. I didn’t know much about this area though, so I set up Good Code to explore what kinds of problems charities have that could be solved by tech. We approach charities that seem high impact (e.g. from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givewell.org/&quot;&gt;GiveWell&lt;/a&gt; recommendations) and then find out what sort of problems they have that could be solved with software. It’s been a good way to start conversations with charities because we’re offering something of use to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;have-the-charities-youve-approached-wanted-the-help&quot;&gt;Have the charities you’ve approached wanted the help?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some charities who I’ve cold emailed haven’t got back to me. But there have been some who have been enthusiastic about getting help. We’ve done the most work with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newincentives.org/&quot;&gt;New Incentives&lt;/a&gt;, who have been &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givewell.org/international/charities/new-incentives&quot;&gt;earmarked by GiveWell&lt;/a&gt; as having the potential to be recommended by them as a top charity in the future. They provide cash incentives to mothers who are at risk of transmitting HIV to their children to get health checks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The projects we’ve done with them have helped improve the efficiency of operations they already do. One project was to automate the process of generating mobile money tokens from their bank account so that they can transfer money to the mothers. This used to be a really laborious manual process, so we helped them save time with that. Another example is that they use google spreadsheets for handling their data, and we’ve helped them out by making some google app scripts for that. It’s been really good that New Incentives have a good understanding of where technology could help out with what they’re doing. This helps a lot with working with them because they can provide good project specifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we’ve wanted to get stuck in quickly and build relationships with charities we’ve tried to go for easy wins where we don’t have to build everything from scratch or maintain it in the long run. It’s been a balancing act between getting the volunteers to commit the time and for the charities to commit the time. So we’ve been testing both sides with smaller projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more ambitious project with New Incentives is a mobile app for field workers for randomising beneficiaries (if demand increases supply limits) and to conduct verification checks including HIV and pregnancy retests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-you-find-volunteers-who-will-do-things&quot;&gt;How do you find volunteers who will do things?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some software developers are just addicted to coding and want to do more, so they can be more committed than other volunteers. But also I’ve tried to put as little time investment into new volunteers as possible and then if they’re keen enough they’ll keep coming back. So it’s more about selecting the right people than motivating people to be productive. Apart from myself, there’s 2 or 3 awesome people committed to doing Good Code projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-dont-the-charities-do-this-work-themselves&quot;&gt;Why don’t the charities do this work themselves?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.againstmalaria.com/&quot;&gt;Against Malaria Foundation&lt;/a&gt; have in-house technical staff, so I don’t know what their reaction would be if we offered to help, although I know GiveDirectly sometimes take on technical volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My impression is that most of the charities don’t have technical staff because it’s not their core activity and they don’t feel it would be worth their while hiring a whole technical staff member to do the kind of small projects we’ve been doing. However, it would be would be worth asking the people at New Incentives whether it would be worth them hiring a software developer in the future. They do have a lot of problems they could solve with tech especially around their mobile money system and their data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-anyone-else-doing-tech-for-high-impact-charities&quot;&gt;Is anyone else doing tech for high impact charities?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a handful of organisations doing similar work, but not focussed on helping the highest impact charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-you-select-charities&quot;&gt;How do you select charities?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to help GiveWell recommended charities, but there also could be promising opportunities elsewhere. There may be charities that don’t need funding so much, but would be able to increase their impact a lot if they had tech help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also really important to think about scale. For example, if you could improve the productivity across the whole of Oxfam the organisation it’s so big that you could have a large impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting example is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thesegovia.com/&quot;&gt;Segovia&lt;/a&gt;. GiveDirectly thought that cash transfer technology wasn’t moving fast enough for them so they set up Segovia to work on this and then sell the technology to other organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the charities we’ve worked with, the solutions to their problems are out there, they just need help implementing them. So the model is closer to IT consulting than to software product development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-you-going-to-do-with-good-code-in-the-medium-term&quot;&gt;What are you going to do with Good Code in the medium term?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve thought if we have the right set of people working on it and enough demand for it, we could set up an agency. And ideally we might be able to develop a product that would be useful for many charities and then scaling that up to have a big impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meetup is also good because it brings together technologists who are interested in Effective Altruism. It’s a good recipe for finding a startup cofounder. I’ve met some really cool people through it and I’m excited about continuing this community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also great to understand these charities on a more intimate level, which normally wouldn’t be possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-you-have-any-needs-what-would-you-like-from-the-good-technology-project&quot;&gt;Do you have any needs? What would you like from the Good Technology Project?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s clear what the effective charities are from GiveWell’s list of giving opportunities. From that, you infer that if we ring them up and they say there’s a problem and we can solve that problem, then it seems like we have had a good amount of impact. But there are maybe other organisations that are high impact and tech constrained that aren’t on GiveWell’s list. So it would be good to have help finding these opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2016 21:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/01/29/tech-for-effective-charities-an-interview-with-ben-clifford-from-good-code</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/01/29/tech-for-effective-charities-an-interview-with-ben-clifford-from-good-code</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Portfolios of the Poor book summary</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-the-book-is-about&quot;&gt;What the book is about&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.portfoliosofthepoor.com/&quot;&gt;Portolios of the Poor&lt;/a&gt; tries to answer the question ‘How do the poor live on $2 a day?’. It’s based on regular interviews with over 250 families in Bangladesh, India, and South Africa which allowed the researchers to build up a detailed picture of the financial transactions these families made. Their main argument is that the poor have sophisticated financial lives. They use many different financial tools that together create ‘financial portfolios’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.portfoliosofthepoor.com/pdf/Chapter1.pdf&quot;&gt;Chapter 1&lt;/a&gt; is available online if you want to get an overview. If you get the book, the most important chapters to read for an overview are chapters one and seven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;poor-peoples-incomes-are-low-and-irregular&quot;&gt;Poor people’s incomes are low and irregular&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People on low incomes have problems not only because they have little money, but also because that their earnings are irregular as they are often casually or self employed. The well-publicised idea of the poor living on $2 a day or less means people often don’t realise that variability of income is a big problem for the poor as well as low income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;poor-people-use-many-financial-tools-to-cope-and-often-create-their-own&quot;&gt;Poor people use many financial tools to cope and often create their own&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;no matter where we looked, we found that most of the households, even those living on less than one dollar a day per person, rarely consume every penny of income as soon as it is earned. They seek, instead, to “manage” their money by saving when they can and borrowing when they need to. They don’t always succeed, but over time, even for the poorest households, a surprisingly large proportion of income gets managed in this way—diverted into savings or used to pay down loans. In the process, a host of different methods are pressed into use: storing savings at home, with others, and with banking institutions; joining savings clubs, savings-and-loan clubs, and insurance clubs; and borrowing from neighbors, relatives, employers, moneylenders, or financial institutions. At any one time, the average poor household
has a fistful of financial relationships on the go.
– p.3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also create their own financial instruments. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotating_savings_and_credit_association&quot;&gt;RoSCAs&lt;/a&gt; are commonly used as a saving method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In a RoSCA the members save the same amount as each other every period - a month, say - and the total amount saved each period is given in whole to one of the members. This continues until everyone has received the “prize” at which point the RoSCA comes naturally to a close - though of course its members may choose to start another cycle immediately or at any later time. – p. 116&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that poor people are creating their own financial instruments suggests that there could be demand for projects that either assist them in this or create better alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;three-needs-drive-much-of-the-financial-activity-of-poor-households&quot;&gt;Three needs drive much of the financial activity of poor households&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Managing basics&lt;/em&gt;: cash-flow management to transform irregular income flows into a dependable resource to meet daily needs.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Coping with risk&lt;/em&gt;: dealing with the emergencies that can derail families with little in reserve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Raising lump sums&lt;/em&gt;: seizing opportunities and paying for bigticket expenses by accumulating usefully large sums of money. – p. 18&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These three needs don’t map cleanly onto borrowing, insurance, and saving as you might expect. Instead, poor households combine many different instruments to meet their needs. For example, they may use both saving and borrowing to manage day-to-day cash flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-financial-instruments-available-to-the-poor-are-often-low-quality&quot;&gt;The financial instruments available to the poor are often low quality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the dominance of the informal sector in the lives of our diary households should not be interpreted to mean that poor households are happy with the instruments available and have no need of anything else. Far from it. – p. 53&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They argue that informal financial instruments have these main weaknesses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unreliability&lt;/em&gt;: Informal financial partners are often poor themselves and so may not have the money you need, when you need it or they may not follow through on their promises. Insecurity is also a problem, with savings sometimes lost or stolen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lack of privacy&lt;/em&gt;: Financial relationships with family and friends can be stressful and a source of shame.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lack of transparency&lt;/em&gt;: The terms of the financial arrangement such as interest are not always clear and people can easily be defrauded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-poor-cant-rely-on-only-insurance-to-manage-risks&quot;&gt;The poor can’t rely on only insurance to manage risks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;there are so many risks, resulting in so many emergencies, that it is unrealistic to expect poor households to contain them by means of the single financial strategy of insurance. Dealing with emergencies is so crucial that even where insurance is available to them, poor households often have to draw down savings and seek loans to make up the losses in full. – p. 19&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;this-area-is-fast-growing-and-may-not-be-neglected&quot;&gt;This area is fast growing and may not be neglected&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Financial services for poor people - that is, microfinance, as provision of these services has become known - is enjoying unprecedented growth. New resources of all sorts are pouring in from every side. More and more providers are setting up shop in more and more countries around the world, some of them fired up by the vision of improving the lives of the poor, others lured by the prospects of profits, and many - the so-called double bottom line institutions - attracted by both. In the last few years, the level of private financial investment has increased sharply so that microfinance is no longer so dependent on the public purse. New technologies, especially mobile devices in the hands of field staff and clients, and smart computer programs in the back offices of providers, promise huge boosts to productivity, lower costs, and greater convenience. Ideas for new financial products for the poor are being launched almost daily, and clever ways of testing their efficiency and their impact are being devised. – p. 175&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-opportunities-to-help&quot;&gt;The opportunities to help&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;helping-poor-households-manage-money-on-a-day-to-day-basis&quot;&gt;Helping poor households manage money on a day-to-day basis&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would involve helping households manipulate “small and irregular or unreliable incomes to ensure that cash is available when needed” to pay for small regular expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A solution for this should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;offer poor households access to a cash-flow management facility that combines convenience with capacity. It would provide the chance to make small-scale savings of any value at any time with the right to withdraw on demand; and at the same time it would offer loans of a modest value that can be taken quickly, on demand, at any time, and repaid in small (and if necessary, irregular) installments. – p. 178&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;helping-poor-households-build-savings-over-the-long-term&quot;&gt;Helping poor households build savings over the long term&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poor people want to save and often have enough money to, and their use of savings clubs like the RoSCAs show that they do save. But existing methods like savings clubs don’t work well over the long term. Long term savings are important for dealing with big events like marriages, purchasing large assets, and dealing with emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, a solution should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;offer long term contractual savings products. These mimic savings clubs by making it possible to save small sums on a regular basis, but add the opportunity of doing so safely over the long term. – p. 179&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;helping-poor-households-borrow-for-all-uses&quot;&gt;Helping poor households borrow for all uses&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;poor households lack dependable access to credit, especially for larger sums that are needed to deal with major life-cycle events, big purchases, and emergencies – p. 179&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a solution should offer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;lending for a wide range of uses. The basic mechanisms are already available, because the development of uncollateralized lending has been the single biggest and most widespread achievement of the microfinance movement. But many microfinance providers still prefer their borrowers to use their loans for just one purpose - microenterprise. Where this is enforced, clients cannot borrow for other vital uses even when they have the cash flow to service the loans. Our own research in Bangladesh, as revealed in the previous chapter, show that many loans ostensibly taken for microenterprises are used for other purposes. It is time for microfinance not merely to face up to this reality, but to embrace the opportunity that it presents. By offering &lt;em&gt;general-purpose&lt;/em&gt; loans, matched in value and structure to the cash flows of poor households, microfinance would open up to the biggest single market it is likely to find among the poor (especially the urban poor who tend to be waged rather than self-employed), and one that would be greatly appreciated by most of our diary households. – p. 179&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;principles-for-designing-a-solution&quot;&gt;Principles for designing a solution&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A solution should be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reliable&lt;/em&gt;: It “should deliver services at the promised time, in the promised amount, and at the promised price”. Most services the poor deal with are unreliable, as are their own incomes. This unreliability makes life harder and having reliable financial partners would help.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Convenient&lt;/em&gt;: It should give the “chance to take and repay loans, and make and withdraw deposits, frequently, close to home or work, quickly, privately, and unobtrusively”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Flexible&lt;/em&gt;: It should be flexible enough that people can use it given their cash flows.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Realistic&lt;/em&gt;: It should offer regularities that promote self-discipline. For example, scheduled visits by bank workers, or planned payment schedules for loans or savings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2016 08:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/01/12/portfolios-of-the-poor-book-summary</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/01/12/portfolios-of-the-poor-book-summary</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What can a technologist do about climate change?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Climate change is a problem that could badly affect the future of humanity so we’d like to learn more about what technologists can do to tackle it. Fortunately, we recently came across &lt;a href=&quot;http://worrydream.com/#!/ClimateChange&quot;&gt;this extremely detailed essay&lt;/a&gt; on what technologists and specifically software engineers can do to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth reading both for its insights about tackling climate change and because it suggests technical solutions that could be applied to problems in many different cause areas. Also, we’ve taken it as inspiration for our own work at Good Technology Project - we would love to create resources as good as this for each cause area we think is promising.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2016 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/01/05/what-can-a-technologist-do-about-climate-change</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://goodtechnologyproject.org/blog/2016/01/05/what-can-a-technologist-do-about-climate-change</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
